<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The answer of the Commission of Generall Assemblie to the quæree propounded to them from the Parliament with an answer of the Commission of the Generall Assemblie to a letter, sent to them from the ministers of the Presbyterie of Sterline.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4199</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35582</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15367882</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15367882</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103541</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33081)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103541)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1148:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The answer of the Commission of Generall Assemblie to the quæree propounded to them from the Parliament with an answer of the Commission of the Generall Assemblie to a letter, sent to them from the ministers of the Presbyterie of Sterline.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
                  <author>Ker, A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by James Brown,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: A. Ker.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103541:1"/>
            <p>THE ANSWER Of the Commiſsion of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſemblie, to
the Quaeree, Propounded to them, from the PARLIAMENT. WITH AN ANSWER Of the
Commiſsion of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Aſſemblie, to a letter, ſent to them, from
the Miniſters of the Preſbyterie of Sterline.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ABERDENE,</hi> Printed by James Brown, 1651.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:103541:2"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>PERTH, 
<date>14 December, 1650. <hi>Ante
meridiem.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <head>Anſwer from the Commiſsion of the Generall
Aſſemblie, to the Quaeree from the PARLIAMENT.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Commiſsion of the Generall Aſſemblie, Having
propounded unto them, from the Honourable Eſtates of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, this
Quaeſtion, <hi>What perſons are to be admitted to ryſe in armes, and
joyne with the forces of the kingdome, and in what capacitie, for defence
thereof, agaynst the armie of Sectaries, who (who contrary to the Solemn League
and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and Treaties) have most vnjustly inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and are destroying
the kingdome?</hi> Doeth hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie returne to their L. this Anſwer:</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:103541:2"/>That, conſidering it is a neceſſarie
duetie incumbent to their L. both by the Law of GOD, and the law of nature, to
uſe all neceſſarie, and lawfull meanes, for the defence of the Libertie,
Lyves, and Eſtates of the people of the Kingdome, agaynſt the publick
enemy, who hath moſt unjuſtly invaded us, and is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying all theſe;
And conſidering that the Forces formerlie rayſed in this kingdom, are ſo
ruined, and ſcattered, that there is not any conſiderable power of them
remayning; And that the enemy hath now in his poſſeſſion, and
altogether under his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, a great part, and that the beſt part of the
kingdom; And that there cannot poſſibly be rayſed out of the reſt of
the Land, any competency of Forces, to oppoſe the enemy, either for
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of theſe parts that are yet free, or for relief of theſe
that are already ſubdued (as is repreſented by the Eſtares) unles there
be a more generall calling foorth of the body of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, then heretofore
hath been; Therefore in this caſe, of ſo great, and evident neceſſity,
we cannot be againſt the raiſing of all Fenſible perſons in the Land,
and permitting them to fight againſt this enemy, for defence of the kingdom;
Excepting ſuch as are excommunicate, fofaulted, notoriouſly prophane, or
flagitious, and ſuch as have been from the beginning, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſtill,
or are at this tyme, obſtinate, and profeſſed enemies, and oppoſers of
the Covenant, &amp; Cauſe of GOD: And for the capacity of acting, That the
Eſtates of Parliamet ought to have, as we hope they will have, ſpeciall
care, that in this ſo generall concurrence of all the people of the kingdom,
none be put in ſuch truſt or power, as may be prejudiciall to the Cauſe
of GOD; And that ſuch Officers as are of known integrity, and affection to
the Cauſe, and particularly, ſuch as have ſuffered in our former armies,
may be taken ſpeciall notice of.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb facs="tcp:103541:3"/>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>PERTH, 
<date>6 <hi>January,</hi> 1651.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <head>The Anſwer of the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the
Generall Aſſemblie, to the 
<note n="*" place="margin">The prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this letter, we thought
might well be ſpared, becauſe of the ſlownes of the Preſs here, and
becaus it is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die printed at Edm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, and is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the hands of
many.</note>letter of the Miniſters of the Preſbyterie of Sterline to
them.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N our letters, ſent from our laſt meeting, to the
ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Presbyteries of this Kirk, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying to them, the reſolutions
of King, and Parliament, to call foorth the bodie of the people, throughout the
parts of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which are yet free from the oppreſſion of the
enemie, for the defence, and delyverance of the kingdome; and deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all
Miniſters, in their places, and ſtations, to contribute their endevours,
for advancing that work, and ſervice: As we did then conceive, ſo do we
ſtill judge, that we did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but what our ductie, in the truſt
committed to us, by the Generall Aſſemblie, for the good of the Kirk, and
peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of GOD, in this kingdome, oblieged us to doe; And that we requyred of
Miniſters, their concurrence, in ſuch ſervice, as the preſent condition
of the kingdome, doeth requyre, and nor onlie, the practiſe of all
Chriſtian Nations, but alſo, both the law of nature, and the Law of GOD,
doeth allow, and<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103541:3"/>approve; Expecting, that the Servants of GOD,
out of their tender affection to the ſuffering, and bleeding condition of
this Kirk, and kingdome, and reſpect to the lawfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of authoritie,
ſhould not been deficient to ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and pious a ſervice: Or,
that if anie ſhould fynd matter of ſcruple, and doubt in the publick
reſolution, concerning that ſervice, which might retard, or put them to a
demurre there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that they would have come, or ſent ſome fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, to
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate their doubts, and ſcruples, with us, that by confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
thereupon, light might have been ſought, for remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of mistakes, rather
then, remayning at diſtance, without neceſſitie, ſent their mynd,
poſitivelie determining, contrary to the publick reſolution in wryting,
which, ordinarilie proves a ſnare, in matters of controverſie, which is not
ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilie winne out of againe, men ſeldome comming off from that, which once
they have in matters of that kynd, put pen to paper on: But no wayes expecting,
that any brethren would have been ſo diſreſpective to the publick
judicatorie of the Kirk, and ſo forward to vndoe peace, and union in the Kirk
of GOD, as to goe up to Pulpits, and preach publicklie, agaynſt the
reſolutions of the publick Iudicatorie, before they had recourſe to
themſelves, to be informed of the grounds, and reaſons of their
reſolutions, and to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate anie doubts, themſelves had upon the
ſame, as to our great griefe, we heare ſome have done. This, as it is
moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderlie, and ſcandalous, ſo it cannot, but at this tyme, be
moſt prejudiciall to the ſafetie of the Kirk, and kingdome, and
advantagious to the deſignes of the publick enemie: And we expect, that
Presbyteries, in their reſpective bounds, will take notice of what hath been
done this way, and reprove it, ſo as the offence may be taken away, and the
prejudice ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viated, ſo farre as may be. As for ſatisfaction to anie
doubts, that are brought agaynſt the preſent publick reſolution, in
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to acting agaynſt the enemie, and reaſons clearing it to be a
duetie, allowed, and approven of GOD, albeit, as we have intimate before, this
might have been more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nientlie<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103541:4"/>done in mutuall conference
together, in the ſpirit of love, and meekeeſſe, then in the way, that is
by ſome choſen: yet ſhall we not refuſe, even in this way, to hold
forth to others, theſe grounds, wherewith we our ſelves were ſatisfied,
and we judge, all in this Kirk, and kingdome, ought to be, and may be
ſatisfied, as alſo to anſwer theſe contrarie reaſons, which have been
brought, and we were not ignorant of, when we agreed upon that
reſolution.</p>
                  <p>And firſt, we ſhall deſyre every one ſeriouſly to
conſider the caſe and condition wherein the kingdome is engaged, &amp;
ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, at this tyme, that now, we are not upon an engagement of
invaſive warre, but upon neceſſary defence againſt a forraigne enemy,
who hath not only injuſtly invaded us, but alſo (through the holy
permiſſive providence of GOD) ſlaine many of our Brethren with the
ſword, ſubdued a great part of the Land, is oppreſſing the people of
GOD therein, and following his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt deſignes, and intentions againſt
the reſt of the kingdome, that in this caſe, in the ordinary way of
providence, according to which men muſt act, unleſſe they would be guilty
of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting GOD, there is need, and ought to be employed againſt the enemy,
ſuch a competency of power, as is requiſit, in right and warrantable
prudencie, &amp; may be had, not being of it ſelfe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: This certainly
is mans duety, what ever GOD, out of His ſoveraignity, hath done, or may doe,
in the caſe of want, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion of meanes: That in ſuch parts of
the kingdome, as are yet free from the oppreſſion of the enemy, and ſo
out of which any men can be raiſed, there is not a poſſibility, to get
ſuch a competencie of power, unleſſe there be a more generall calling
foorth of the body of the people, then hath been before, this as it is moſt
certaine in it ſelfe, ſo it is moſt apparent, and evident unto all, that
doe underſtand theſe parts of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and whereas faithfull, and
honeſt men in the State, well acquainted with the ſeverall ſhyres of that
part of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, have publickly declared, that, when all ſhall be
brought together, that can be called foorth of theſe parts, according to
publick reſolution, will ſcarce be a competent power, againſt 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103541:4"/>the power of the enemy, we cannot but much wonder, if any not
ſo acquainted therewith, ſhall hold the contrary, and not give credit to
the declaration of honeſt, and faithfull men, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciallie in authority,
the matter being ſuch, as in the immediat knowledge thereof, dependeth on
ſenſe, &amp; as to theſe that have not that knowledge, pertaineth to
humane faith, which giveth credit to the teſtimony <hi>teſtium
idoneorum,</hi> of competent witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſuch as theſe are whom we haue
deſigned: So that the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in their letter, whileas for aſſerting
the exerciſing of their judgement anent this point, of the neceſſity of
the kingdom, in a way of diſſenting from the publick declaration, &amp;
teſtimony given thereanent, they doe alledge the practiſe of the Generall
Aſſembly 1648, deſiring the Parliament to ſatisfie, and cleare them in
the lawfulneſſe, and neceſſity of the warre, ſeeme not to argue to
the purpoſe, becauſe there the queſtion was about a point <hi>de
jure,</hi> here the queſtion is about the exiſtence of phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall
meanes.</p>
                  <p>The caſe of the kingdom ſtanding thus, the queſtion is,
whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be a lawfull courſe or not, to raiſe all ſenſible
perſons, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged ſubjects of the kingdom, according as is
expreſſed in the publick reſolution for defence, and deliverance of the
kingdom, from the unjuſt violence &amp; oppreſſion of a forraigne enemy?
We judge the courſe not only to be lawfull, but neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary duetie in the
caſe, for theſe reaſons: 1. Becauſe it hath been through all
generations, and is at this day, the univerſall, uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted practiſe of
all chriſtian kingdoms, and States, in caſe of juſt defence, againſt
forraign invaſion, to employ all ſuch as are acknowledged ſubjects, and
citicens, in ſuch a way, as is not evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently deſtructive to Religion,
which practiſe, is alſo allowed, and approven by the judgement of the
ſoundeſt Divines in the Proteſtant Kirks, as might be particularly,
inſtanced, if need were, in this paper. We doe not leane our faith, in
matters of conſcience, upon the practiſes, or teſtimonies of men, yet
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that ſo univerſall a practiſe, in a matter of conſcience,
uncontroverted, ought not to be miſregarded, and ſeems is ſo farre from
being ſo horrid a ſinne, as ſome account it, that it<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103541:5"/>cannot want good &amp; clear reaſon for it: And here we ſhal
deſire that the practiſe of our own firſt reformers of this Kirk, may be
called to mynd, who did receiue ſundry unto co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells, &amp;
acting with them, againſt the Queen Regents faction, who had been before upon
her part and faction, oppoſing the Congregation, when as they came to
acknowledgement of their former errours, &amp; were willing to joyn with the
Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, in the good cauſe. 2. As the law of nature binds &amp;
obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges every one, that is a member of the politicall body of a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or
State, to endevour, to the uttermoſt of their power, the preſervation of
the whole, &amp; of other fellow members, in a juſt quarrell, &amp; cauſe,
which if they refuſe to doe, they are guilty of murther, and treachery
againſt the Common-wealth: So the ſame law of nature allowes the body,
&amp; layes an obligation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch, as are governours &amp; rulers of that
body, to call for the help and aſſiſtance of every member, as neceſsity
requireth, for defence &amp; deliverance of the body, from injuſt violence
&amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, which if they doe not, they run into the ſame
guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; betray their truſt: Or, to make the matter more
clear, take this formed argument: That which any is obliged to doe for anothers
preſervation, and cannot omit, without the guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of anothers
deſtruction, that may the other lawfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of him, when he needeth it,
and when it may be done by him, without the undoing of a greater good, then is
the others preſervation: But ſo it is, that every ſubject of the kingdom,
is obliged by the law of nature, their oath of allegeance, their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants,
the Law of GOD, to endevour, to the uttermoſt of their power, the
preſervation of the kingdom, againſt injuſt viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: Therefore
their helpe may be lawfully called for by ſuch as are in authority, for this
end, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; the kingdoms preſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtands in need of it, &amp;
their help tends not to the undoing of a greater good, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the
preſervation of the ſafety of the kingdom. But, to aſſume in way of
proſyllogiſme, the preſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſafety of the kingdom, at this
tyme, againſt injuſt violence, ſtands in need of the help of many
ſubjects, who haue been formerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ryſing in arms, &amp; their
power may be employed for<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103541:5"/>that end, without the undoing of a
greater good, as ſhall be clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red afterward, in anſwering the objectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s:
Therefore, &amp;c. 3. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we have, in the ſincerity of our hearts, adviſed
with the Word of GOD, we can find nothing therin contrary to the courſe, in
the caſewe have propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded: And how could we find otherwiſe, ſeing the
law of nature (which is comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the Word of GOD, as a part of it) is
ſo clear for it? But we doe find in the Word, good and clear warrant for it:
We ſhall not ſtay upon all which might be brought thence, but ſhall only
point at one or two particulars, which ſpeaking clearly to the point, may be
ſufficient to build faith vpon. 1. We find in the book of <hi>Judges,</hi>
when, becauſe of great defection from the purity of Religion, &amp; the
Covena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of GOD in that ancient Kirk, they were broght under the oppreſsion
of forraign enemies; yet, when as any go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour was raiſed up by GOD, for
their defence, &amp; deliverace fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oppreſsion, &amp; the people are
raiſed, &amp; gathered out for that end, we find them all called out
promiſcuouſly, not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a great part of them, no queſtion, had
been in the defectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, And it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſaid, without groundles raſhnes,
that al ſuch had given convincing evidences of true repentance: Neither do we
find that any of their governors are reproved, for not excluding ſuch as had
been in the defection, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ryſing in arms, for the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary defence
&amp; deliverance of the Land: But on the contrary, we find ſad reproofs,
&amp; terrible curſes, pronounced againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that came not out
ot the work; <hi>Judg.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 15.16.17.23. And who will ſay,
that there were none amongſt theſe mentioned there, had been in the
defection? 2. The like may be ſeen in the hiſtory of the <hi>Kings</hi>
&amp; <hi>Chronicles,</hi> that, when after a defection fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, &amp;
the Covena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of GOD, gracious reforming kings aroſe, &amp; had to doe
againſt forraign invaſion, we find not theſe kings debarring any
ſubjects, but calling them out promiſcuouſly, for the juſt &amp;
neceſſary defence of the kingdom: Neither do we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver find it laid to their
charge, that they called out ſuch, or ſuch ſubjects, upon that ſervice,
though we may clearly perceive by the ſtory, &amp; ſermons of the
<hi>Prophets</hi> of the times, that in time of beſt kings, &amp; beſt
reformations, the greater part of the body of<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103541:6"/>the people were
very wicked, &amp; ſtill retaining in their practiſe, much
ſuperſtition: Inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces are well known to ſuch as have any acquaintance
in Scripture. 3. We find a very clear practiſe, ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with divine
approbation, and followed with the LORDS bleſsing making it ſuccesfull,
ſpeaking aboundantly to our point, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. Where, in the caſe
of <hi>Jabeſh-gilead,</hi> beſieged by a forraign enemy, <hi>Saul</hi>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands all <hi>Iſrael</hi> to come forth, for the defence &amp; delivery of
their brethren, under pain of a ſevere ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill cenſure: Wherein we deſire
theſe things to be conſidered. 1. That what <hi>Saul</hi> did in this
buſines, was by the motion of the Spirit of GOD; to wit, acting him to doe
the duety of his Royall calling. 2. That what the people did in obedience to
the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, they were alſo moved thereunto of GOD, by an impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of
his fear, making the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to wit, to revere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the authority of the king, called
by him, &amp; now acting his calling. 3. That in this acting, <hi>Samuel</hi>
is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>curring, &amp; acting jointly with <hi>Saul,</hi> without making any
oppoſition to the courſe that is taken. 4. As all the body of the people is
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to riſe, ſo all come forth as one man, &amp; yet <hi>Cap.</hi>
10. <hi>v. ult.</hi> many amongſt them (as is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent a great faction) were
ſonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi> wicked &amp; turbulent perſons, who malignantly
oppoſed the work, &amp; clear revealed will of GOD, in calling <hi>Saul</hi>
to the governement of his people. We deſire that <hi>Calvins</hi> ſermons
on that chapter be read, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, amongſt other things that make to our
purpoſe, it will be found, that that learned, judicious, &amp; pious writer,
doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demn the citizens of <hi>Jabeſh-gilead,</hi> of much ſinfulnes, for
that they were ſo ſoon ready to yeeld unto, &amp; capitulat with the enemy,
&amp; did not firſt pray to GOD, and <hi>call for the help of their
brethre,</hi> the like whereof, we are ſory, that the courſes of ſome in
this Land, at leaſt in <hi>the condition of the work,</hi> leads unto,
whileas the neceſſary help of fellow ſubjects againſt an invading &amp;
oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing enemy, is not only not called for, but rejected, &amp;
oppoſed by them. 4. To reaſon in a more particular way to our caſe, in
<hi>hypotheſi,</hi> we deſire it may be conſidered, that ſuch as are
exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, who are a great part of the remnant of the Land, If not the greater
part, if rules of excluſion, as they are urged in the letter, be extended,
and applyed equally, &amp; impartially, having their<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103541:6"/>lives,
liberties, and eſtates allowed unto them, muſt either be in theſe things
enſured (we mean in ſo farre as is competent to man to doe) by
interpoſing a competent power, for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection againſt the violence,
or, if that cannot be given them, as certainly it cannot be given, as the
condition of this Land now ſtandeth, they muſt be allowed to act for their
defence, <hi>nam qui dat vitam, dat neceſſaria, &amp; conſequentia ad
vitam:</hi> Now how ſhall they act, and take up armes for their own defence,
and the defence of the countrey, if they be not called thereunto, and allowed
by authoritie? If it ſhall be ſaid, that they may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to act for
their own defence, we repone, that muſt either be in a joint way with others
in the Land, &amp; if ſo, then the thing in queſtion is granted upon the
matter, but in a way diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and more dangerous, then that which is
deſired, and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon: Or apart, and by themſelves: Certainly that
were a more ready way, as the condition of the Land now ſtandeth, to expoſe
both themſelves, and others, and the whole Land, to ruine, and wee haue
alreadie found too ſad experience of acting this way.</p>
                  <p>We come now to anſwer the reaſons, &amp; objections, brought
on the contrary; And firſt, we obſerve, that no teſtimonies or grounds of
Scripture, are alledged in an head by themſelves, againſt the reſolution,
to ſhow that it is a courſe ſinfull in it ſelf: Only in the firſt
branch of the ſecond reaſon, ſome are pointed at, which were made uſe
of <hi>anno</hi> 1648, againſt the aſſociating with <hi>Malignants,</hi>
in the engagement againſt <hi>England,</hi> and are alledged alſo to
ſpeak much againſt the preſent buſines: But it is not ſufficient to
ſay, and dictat this, it ought to have been cleared, if it could been: But
the caſes are very much different, that was of an invaſive warre, wherein
an aſſociation with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants,</hi> notourly continuing in their
<hi>malignant</hi> courſes, and that without any neceſſity, there being
ſufficiency of honeſt men to have been employed, had the cauſe been good,
this is of juſt and neceſſary defence, againſt forraign prevaling
invaſion, and oppreſsion, wherein tho, none are to be employed, that
conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in a courſe of <hi>malignancie:</hi> The places pointed at, may
well<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103541:7"/>ſpeak againſt that, but doe not reach this. We need
ſay no more, unleſſe there were ſome ſhow of proofe to the contrary,
yet we ſhall ſay ſomewhat particularly to one place, that which is ſaid
in the caſe of <hi>Amaziahs</hi> aſſociating with, and taking to him the
<hi>Iſraelits,</hi> for help in his juſt defence, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.7.
<hi>O King, let not the army of Iſrael goe with thee, for the LORD is not
with Iſrael, even with all the houſe of Ephraim,</hi> as being mainly
urged, and ſeems moſt to ſtick with ſome in the preſent
buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to which ſundry things may be anſwered, which clear the
preſent buſineſſe from the force thereof. 1. The <hi>Iſraelits</hi>
were idolaters, and forrainers, not ſo in our caſe, in either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect:
But it is alledged, that the reaſon why <hi>Amaziah</hi> is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
from taking their aſsiſtance, is, Becauſe GOD was not with them, and
therefore the ſame reaſon, having place in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of theſe, whom the
preſent reſolution comprehendeth, the diſſwaſion hath the ſame
force againſt them. Therefore 2. GOD'S not being with them, may be either
conceived and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, in regard of the eſtate of grace, and
reconciliation with GOD, but how-ſo-ever that with many of them GOD was not,
in this regard, yet the reaſon cannot be alledged in this ſenſe,
becauſe then it would follow by the argument, that we might not take the help
of any man out of the eſtate of grace, for our juſt and neceſſary
defence, which none will admit; or, it may be underſtood of GOD'S
aſsiſtance, and proſpering pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence ſimply: But neither can it be
taken thus, becauſe it is certain and clear, that GOD was often with them in
this ſenſe, in their own cauſe and quarrells, therefore it muſt needs
be conceived, in regard of their profeſſion, and Religion, which was
corrupt, and idolatrous, Now the reaſon thus underſtood, hath not place in
our buſineſſe. 3. Yet doe we not find, that <hi>Amaziah</hi> is commanded
to exclude any of the ſubjects of his own kingdom, from acting in that
defence, or reproved for not doing of it, notwithſtanding many of them, no
doubt, were naughty, and corrupt in their way, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 14.4.</p>
                  <p>The firſt reaſon, is taken from the fourth article of the
Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, that the reſolution agreed upon, is inconſiſtent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, 
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103541:7"/>the ſcope whereof, is alledged to be againſt the
employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch perſons, becauſe it byndeth to diſcover them, and
b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing them to condign puniſhment,
which is a further degree of diſtance: To which we anſwer, No perſons
that are ſuch, as are deſcrived in that article, are allowed to be
employed, or, we hope, ſhall be employed: Or, if any ſuch be employed, we
think it our duety, to teſtifie againſt them, yet doe we not think, that
were a ſufficient ground or warrant, for any godly, and honeſt ſubject,
to withdraw their concurrence, from defending their countrey, in a juſt
cauſe, when called thereunto by lawfull au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie: But, if any, who have
been ſometyme ſuch, and having been cenſured, as hath been judged
convenient by the ſupreme judicatories, or have been pardoned, doe now
renounce, and engage themſelves againſt ſuch courſes, by all the moſt
ſolemn tyes, that can be impoſed upon men, or not found notourly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane,
or flagitious, and are acknowledged members of State, and Kirk, be employed,
according to clear bound duety, for the juſt and neceſſary defence of the
kingdom, that article, to our capacitie, ſpeaketh nothing againſt this.</p>
                  <p>To the ſecond, Alledging the way that is taken, to be
againſt former publick reſolutions, declarations, our ſolemn engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
&amp;c. we ſhall not need to inſiſt in following ſeverally every branch
thereof, becauſe all of them may be cleared, by ſome common
conſiderations. 1. Our firſt declarations, and publick reſolutions, and
engagements concerning this matter, were conceived in relation to acting, in a
way of proſecution of the cauſe, and no wayes intended to the prejudice of
juſt and neceſſarie defence of the kingdom, againſt forraign
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions, for which we are allowed and bound by the law of nature (which no
humane lawes or reſolutions can infringe or prejudge) to make uſe of all
ſubjects in the kingdom, if the making uſe of them be not ſinfull in it
ſelfe, and may be without prejudice of the cauſe. And here, we deſire it
may be remembred, that in the beginning of theſe troubles, <hi>anno</hi>
1638, when as there were then ſtanding lawes in this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which are not
yet repealed to this day, diſcharging all<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103541:8"/>ſubjects from
ryſing in armes, without the kings expreſſe war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and command: Yet the
ſubjects of this kingdom, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving themſelves in danger to be
deſtroyed by forraign inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, did fynd theſe lawes no wayes to bynd up
their hands, from taking armes, for their juſt defence, and ſelfe
preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, theſe lawes, in the intention of the law-giver, being made
for the preſervation of the kingdom, and not for the deſtruction of it: And
accordingly, when the pacification was made at BERWICK, they refuſed to take
a Pardon for what they had done, in taking armes, not only without, but
againſt the kings command, alledging and that truelie, that they had not
broken the law, in regard they had but obeyed the law of nature, in a caſe of
neceſſitie, in prejudice of which, theſe lawes could not be conceived to
be made: And we conceive the verie ſame is applicable to our former
reſolutions, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, &amp;c. in relation to our preſent caſe. 2.
What is ſayd in latter declarations concerning this matter, in relation even
to defence agaynſt our invaders, as it ſtreatcheth further, then the
declared intention of former reſolutions, ſo it was in a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yme, when the whole kingdom was
inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re, and there might be a
choiſe made of inſtruments to act, and we confeſſe, in ſuch a caſe
choiſe ſhould be made, of the beſt inſtruments, but now the caſe is
altered, And as to the anſwer given by the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion at STERLINE to the
Quaeree propounded by the Kings Majeſtie, about the end of September, the
lyke may be ſayd, there being then conſiderable forces gathered in the
WEST, by whom much was expected, by honeſt people, and the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of the
armie which were as STERLINE, and on this ſyde, together with ſuch recruits
as were then a levying, being joyned together, might have been a conſiderable
power, to have oppoſed the enemie without any urgent neceſſitie to
em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy others. Yet 3. neither at this tyme is it reſolved that anie be
employed, that are either knownly prophane, or continuing in enmitie and
oppoſition to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and cauſe of
God.</p>
                  <p>To the third, Taken from the eminent danger, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
will inevitable follow the way reſolved upon, becauſe<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103541:8"/>theſe men, getting power into their hands, cannot but employ the
ſame, according to their own principles, and for eſtabliſhing their own
ends, deſtructive to the Work of GOD, We anſwer, 1. Suppoſe there be
ſome danger of this kynd, yet it is not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn, and inevitable; And we
deſyre it may be conſidered, that on the other hand, if neceſſarie
help, in it ſelf not ſinfull, be not employed, there is certayn ruine, both
to kingdom, and cauſe, without an extraordinarie divine work, which we have
no warrant to look for, neglecting ordinarie means: Let theſe two be weighed
in the ballance, one agaynſt another, and let warrantable Chriſtian
prudence judge, which of them were to be choſen. 2. We cannot ſee the
danger unto the Cauſe of GOD, ſo apparent, and great, by this way of
defence of the kingdom, Conſidering 1. That manie of theſe now to be
em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed therein, who have been debarred, were formerlie known active
favourers, and promoters of the cauſe, and haue ſolemnlie declared their
acknowledgement of the ſinfulneſſe of their fall from their
ſteadfaſtneſſe, and their ſorrow for the ſame, and have bound
themſelves, to a more firm and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full adhering to the cauſe, and
Covenant, by all the bands, that can be impoſed upon men. 2. That none are to
be employed, who are known to be ſtill of a contrarie Mynd and affection. 3.
That none, of whom there may be the leaſt ſuſpicion this way are to get
ſuch power, or truſt put in their hand, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the kingdome, as may
be prejudiciall to the cauſe. 4. For preventing anie danger of this kynd, we
reſolve to have a particular oath, to be tendered unto, and taken by all, who
are to be on the ſervice, as full, and bynding, as poſſiblie men can
conceive, to guard the cauſe of GOD, and work of reformation from all harm or
prejudice. 5. The oppoſition that manie of theſe, who have been formerlie
excluded, and now are to be admitted, did make to the cauſe of GOD, did
aryſe upon their ſinfull preference of the kings intereſt, to the
cauſe, which were then ſeparated, and ſtanding in oppoſition one to
another: But now the intereſt of the king, and the cauſe, being joyned in
one, and the king now having bound himſelf<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103541:9"/>by Covenant, and
oaths, ſolemnlie renewed, at his Coronation, to maintain the Covenant, and
cauſe, there cannot be ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent danger apprehended that way.</p>
                  <p>To the fourth, Taken from ſcandall and offence of the godlie,
It is anſwered, 1. The meanes reſolved on, being not ſinfull in it
ſelf, and being neceſſarie in the preſent caſe and condition of the
Land, the offence and ſcandall cannot be GIVEN, but TAKEN: And therefore. 2.
If anie godlie ſhall with-draw themſelves, from contributing their
neceſſarie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence, for the defence of the kingdom, they cannot but
highlie ſinne agaynſt GOD, in deſerting their neceſſarie due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and
we doe wiſh, and hope, that there be no active inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to cauſe
honeſt and godlie people in the Land to ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and offend more, then
either they of themſelves are incly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to doe, or they can have occaſion
by the publick reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 3. Suppoſe the Magiſtrate ſhould employ
ſome perſons whom he ought not, yet we doe not ſee, how that anie godlie
ought, or could, without ſinne, lye aback from concurring in the juſt
defence of their countrey, in the neceſſitie thereof, and being called by
lawfull authoritie.</p>
                  <p>To the fifth, Wherein it is ſayd, That it ſeemeth to make
voyd the ſtrength of ſeverall anſwers, given to the adverſarie,
alledging, our acceſſion to the unlawfull engagement, and to promoting a
malignant partie, and intereſt, and to contribute to the juſtifying of
their quarrell, and to heighten them in their hopes, and reſolutions
agaynſt this Land, It is anſwered, 1. It can no wayes favour anie
alledgeance of the adverſarie, of our acceſſion to the unlawfull
engagement, or promoting of anie malignant partie, or intereſt, ſeing none
are to bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, who have been acceſſorie to the engagement, but
ſuch, as have ſolemnlie, and publicklie renounced the ſame, and all
courſes tending thereto, and make declaration of their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of
the ſinfulneſſe, and unlawfulneſſe thereof, doe engage themſelves
never to come anie way in oppoſition to the Covenant, and cauſe of GOD. 2.
Wee ſee not how it can any way juſtifie their quarrell, &amp; we wiſh
that none amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt <pb n="17" facs="tcp:103541:9"/>our ſelves had given, or doe give them
injuſtlie, pretences of juſtifying their quarrell. 3. We muſt not ſtand
to make uſe of lawfull and neceſſarie meanes, for our juſt Defence,
upon their conceiving groundles bigge hopes, and injuſt reſolutions
agaynſt us.</p>
                  <p>To the ſixth, What is alledged therein, is as eaſilie denyed
as it is affirmed: And here we cannot but obſerve, that, which is generallie
throughout this whole letter, that all, who have been hitherto debarred from
acting, what ever they have been before, and what ever be their teſtimonies
now of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, for anie ſinfull courſe they have been upon, for a
tyme, for which they have given ſatisfaction to the KIRK, are yet counted
<hi>Malignants,</hi> which we cannot but think a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie hard, and uncharitable
judgement, and the rather, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that in the Commiſſion at STERLINE,
after the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat, it was otherwyſe publicklie acknowledged.</p>
                  <p>To the ſeventh, 1. We acknowledge, that we have cauſe to be
affrayed of the LORDS indignation, and controverſie agaynſt the Land, both
for the ſinnes of ſuch as are now to be employed, as alſo for the
ſinnes of others, as well as of them; but we ſee no cauſe to bee affrayed
of GODS indignation, ſimplie upon this account, that neceſſarie meanes,
allowed by the Law of GOD, and the law of nature, be made uſe of, for our
juſt and neceſſarie defence: And as for that enemie, he is not onlie the
Rod of GODS anger, and the Staffe in His Hand the LORDS indignation, agaynſt
<hi>Malignants;</hi> but alſo agaynſt the whole Land, even the godlie
themſelves, as is at this day viſible, in all the three kingdomes,
becauſe of our manyfold ſinnes, hypocriſies, and diſobedience to the
Goſpell of CHRIST; So, if this alledgeance have anie force to the poynt, for
which it is brought, it ſhould follow, that all and everie one of us ſhould
lye down, and doe nothing agaynſt the enemy at all: Certainly, although
<hi>Aſhur</hi> was the Rod of GODS anger agaynſt the hypocriticall nation
of the IEWES, yet that was no argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t why that people might not ſtand in
their defence agaynſt that enemie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:103541:10"/>Whereas it is ſayd, That the
neceſſitie pleaded for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent reſolution, doeth not cleare them
in theſe thinges, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they remember in the year 1646. albeit the
neceſsitie was pleaded by the COMMITTEE of ESTATES, for the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulation
with IAMES GRAHAME, and his adherents, yet that did not hinder the COMMISSION,
to beare teſtimonie againſt the pardoning of them, which was much leſſe
then employing them, It is anſwered, 1. That the neceſsitie being cleare
(as it hath been cleared in the preſent caſe) Pleadeth moſt ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
for, and may cleare anie concerning the making uſe of meanes, in themſelves
lawfull, for juſt defence. 2. That ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie, pleaded by the COMMITTEE of
ESTATES, was meerelie pretended, they having then ſufficiencie of power to
have ſuppreſſed, and taken order with that enemie. What is alledged from
the paſſages, and papers alreadie cited, as ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king agaynſt the
employing of them in our Armie, in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Kingdome, hath been
alreadie ſufficientlie anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. That which followeth, ſpoken agaynſt
unbeliefe, in caſe of the ſcarceneſſe of meanes, &amp;c. Wee
acknowledge the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Trueth of that, that it is all one with GOD to ſave
with manie, or with few, and that it is great ſinne, to be misbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,
when GOD in His Providence redacteth us to ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſecundarie meanes,
but that it is no ground for us, to neglect the uſe of lawfull,
neceſſarie, and competent meanes, when GOD doeth afford them, ſuch as He
hath yet, Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be His Name, left unto us in this Land. But none of
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, whom wee meet with, doe ſee, how theſe can be had,
without ſuch a calling forth of the people in theſe parts of the Land, that
are yet free from the oppreſsion of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, as is held forth in the
publick reſolution, which being made uſe of, as they may be made uſe of,
without ſuch ſnares, dangers to the cauſe of GOD, and any given
ſcandall, and juſt griefe to the godlie, as is pretended, what ever be the
event thereupon, give us leave to ſay, will be more peace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to us,
then if anie further calamitie ſhould come upon the Land, lawfull and
neceſſarie meanes affoorded by providence,<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103541:10"/>not having
been made uſe of. What followeth here-after, hath been anſwered before,
untill it come to theſe wordes, <hi>But wee cannot conceave how the Kingdome
and Cauſe can bee well ſeparated,</hi> &amp;c. Wherein, give us leave to
ſay, without offence, great injurie is done the COMMISSION of the KIRK, in
that reſolution, whileas it is alledged, that therein we doe ſeparate the
kingdome, from the Cauſe, as we were going contrarie to the mynd and courſe
of this KIRK and Kingdome, theſe twelve yeares paſt, which never
ſeparated them, and were homologating with ſuch, as being adverſaries,
and undermyners of the Cauſe, have endevoured to put Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion out of the
quarrell. Doeth our mentioning onlie the kingdome in that reſolution, import
a ſeparation of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the Cauſe, in the quarrell agaynſt our
enemie? Or what Logick can draw out ſuch a conſequence out of it? Wee doe
think, that the kingdome being in danger by this enemie, the Cauſe alſo is
in danger, and the defending of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, will be the defending of the
Cauſe alſo: And wee truſt no inſtruments ſhall bee employed for the
defence of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to the prejudice of the Cauſe: So that wee ſee
not that much advantage is by that reſolution given to the enemie, and wee
wonder how it can bee ſayd, to bee inductive to others, to comply with them,
to the prejudice of the kingdome, as being of leſſe value and importance,
then the Cauſe, except theſe others, be ſuch, as have caſt off naturall
affection to their native kingdome, or judge theſe who are preſent enemies
to the kingdome, not to bee enemies to the Cauſe.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>PERTH 
<date>MARCH 13. 1651.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe Letter of the Ministers of the Preſbyterie of Stirling is
not here printed as was intended, The ſame being already printed at
Edinburgh, vnder the falſe and odious title of <hi>A Remonſtrance of the
Presbytery of Stirling againſt the preſent conjunction with the Malignant
partie,</hi> and ſpread throughout the Kingdom by what meanes and warrand
it's not known.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
